Shounak Datta

Indian Statistical Institute 203, B. T. Road, Baranagar Kolkata 700108 India

email: shounak.jaduniv@gmail.com

shounak_r.isical.ac.in
Phone: (+91)-9674298047
URL: https://shounak-d.github.io/



Areas of specialization

Machine Learning * Imbalanced Classification * Missing Features * Absent Features * Clustering * Constrained Optimization * Multi-objective Optimization * Evolutionary Computation

Research interests & experience

I have been working on machine learning, data mining and stochastic optimization for 7 years now. This has not only lent me insights regarding the nature of data but has also helped me clearly understand the principal data analysis mechanisms viz. classification, clustering, dimensionality reduction, etc. and their relationships with mathematical optimization problems. I have also garnered a fair amount of knowledge regarding convex as well as non-convex optimization problems and techniques (including constrained and unconstrained evolutionary optimization and multi-objective optimization) which can be used to solve the complex optimization paradigms often posed by data analysis tasks.

My current research interests include development of learning algorithms that are resilient to the various irregularities characterizing real-world data, such as class imbalance, presence of small disjuncts within classes, missing feature values, etc. I am also interested in multi-objective optimization based formulations of traditional machine learning tasks to overcome the shortcomings imposed by the single-objective optimization frameworks. For instance, I have helped create a fuzzy partitional clustering algorithm, using multi-objective optimization, which can automatically determine the level of fuzziness corresponding to the data available for the task at hand.

I am currently also taking interest in computer vision which has been revolutionized by the latest advances in deep learning. I believe such applications to be very relevant as they directly impact our quality of life. This has led me to employ some of the state-of-the-art deep classifiers in my latest projects.

I have supervised 20+ undergraduate and postgraduate research interns (from various notable academic institutes such as ISI, Jadavpur University, IIT Guwahati, IIIT Guwahati, IIEST, etc.) on projects leading to papers, technical reports and dissertations since 2013.

Selected research projects

2013-now

2015-now

Some of the more interesting research projects I have worked on are:

Developing learning algorithms resilient to data irregularities such as class imbalance, small disjuncts, missing features, Electronics and Communication Sciences Unit, Indian Statistical Institute, Kolkata, India.

Developing fuzzy partitional clustering methods which can automatically determine the required level of fuzziness, Electronics and Communication Sciences Unit, Indian Statistical Institute, Kolkata, India.

1

Shounak Datta Indian Statistical Institute (+91) -9674298047 shounak.jaduniv@gmail.com

- 2011-2013 Analysis and predicting of stock market indices, Department of Electronics and Telecommunication, Jadavpur University, Kolkata, India.
- Developing electrooculogram based control mechanisms for wheelchair to facilitate rehabilitation, Department of Electronics and Telecommunication jointly with the School of Bioscience and Engineering, Jadavpur University, Kolkata, India.

Positions held

2015-now Senior Research Fellow, Indian Statistical Institute, Kolkata, India. 2013-2015 Junior Research Fellow, Indian Statistical Institute, Kolkata, India.

Education

- 2013-now Ph.D. in Computer Science, *On the Design of Learning Systems with Resilience to Data Irregularities*, Indian Statistical Institute, Kolkata, India, under the supervision of Prof. (Dr.) Swagatam Das
- M.E. in Electronics and Telecommunication Engineering (Specialization: Control Engineering), Jadavpur University, Kolkata, India.
- B.Тесн. in Electronics and Communication Engineering, Maulana Abul Kalam Azad University of Technology, Kolkata, India.

Programming Languages & Tools

MATLAB coding experience for 10+ years.

Knowledge of Python coding using numpy, scipy, etc.

Knowledge of employing deep learning algorithms using Python and Keras.

Comfortable with programming using C/C++ as required.

Extensive experience of preparing articles and presentations using LTFX.

Publications

The following is a list of my research articles including 8 journal- and 4 peer-reviewed conference-papers. For more details please visit my Google Scholar page at

https://scholar.google.co.in/citations?user=qtW4ugoAAAAJ

JOURNAL ARTICLES

- "Clustering with Missing Features: A Penalized Dissimilarity Measure based approach", Shounak Datta, Supritam Bhattacharjee, Swagatam Das, *Machine Learning*.
- "Handling data irregularities in classification: Foundations, trends, and future challenges", Swagatam Das, Shounak Datta, Bidyut B. Chaudhuri, *Pattern Recognition* 81, 674-693.
- "Adaptive Learning-Based k-Nearest Neighbor Classifiers With Resilience to Class Imbalance", Sankha Subhra Mullick, Shounak Datta, Swagatam Das, *IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks and Learning Systems*.
- "Generalized mean based back-propagation of errors for ambiguity resolution", Shounak Datta, Sankha Subhra Mullick, Swagatam Das, *Pattern Recognition Letters* 94, 22-29.
- "A Radial Boundary Intersection aided interior point method for multi-objective optimization", Shounak Datta, Abhiroop Ghosh, Krishnendu Sanyal, Swagatam Das, *Information Sciences* 377, 1-16.
- "A feature weighted penalty based dissimilarity measure for k-nearest neighbor classification with missing features", Shounak Datta, Debaleena Misra, Swagatam Das, *Pattern Recognition Letters* 80, 231-237.

- "Near-Bayesian Support Vector Machines for imbalanced data classification with equal or unequal misclassification costs", Shounak Datta, Swagatam Das, *Neural Networks* 70, 39-52.
- "Development strategy of eye movement controlled rehabilitation aid using Electro-oculogram", Anwesha Banerjee, Shounak Datta, Amit Konar, D. N. Tibarewala", *International Journal of Scientific and Engineering Research* 3 (6), 1-6.

Conference articles

- "Rough-Fuzzy Collaborative Multi-level Image Thresholding: A Differential Evolution Approach", Sujoy Paul, Shounak Datta, Swagatam Das, MENDEL 2015, Proceedings of, 329-341.
- "Real time electro-oculogram driven rehabilitation aid", Anwesha Banerjee, Pratyusha Das, Shounak Datta, Amit Konar, Ramadoss Janarthanan, D. N. Tibarewala", *International Conference on Advances in Computing, Proceedings of the*, 435-440.
- "Single channel electrooculogram (EOG) based interface for mobility aid", Anwesha Banerjee, Sumantra Chakraborty, Pratyusha Das, Shounak Datta, Amit Konar, D. N. Tibarewala", Intelligent Human Computer Interaction (IHCI), Proceedings of the 4th International Connference on, 1-6.
- "Electrooculogram based online control signal generation for wheelchair", Anwesha Banerjee, Shounak Datta, Pratyusha Das, Amit Konar, D. N. Tibarewala, Ramadoss Janarthanan, Electronic System Design (ISED), Proceedings of the International Symposium on, 251-255.

DISSERTATION

"Analysis and prediction of time series indices obtained from stock market indices", Shounak Datta, under the guidance of Amit Konar, *M.E. Dissertation*, Jadavpur University, Kolkata, India.

PREPRINTS

- "Diversifying Support Vector Machines for Boosting using Kernel Perturbation: Applications to Class Imbalance and Small Disjuncts", communicated after revision to IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks and Learning Systems, Shounak Datta, Sayak Nag, Sankha Subhra Mullick, Swagatam Das, arXiv 1712.08493.
- "On Boosting, Tug of War, and Lexicographic Programming", under revision for publication in IEEE Transactions on Knowledge and Data Engineering, Shounak Datta, Sayak Nag, Swagatam Das, arXiv 1708.09684.

Unpublished manuscripts

- "On Convergence of the Class Membership Estimator in Fuzzy k-Nearest Neighbor Classifier", communicated to IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks and Learning Systems, Sankha Subhra Mullick, Shounak Datta, Sourish Dhekane, Swagatam Das.
- "Fuzzy Clustering to Identify Clusters at Different Levels of Fuzziness: An Evolutionary Multi-Objective Optimization Approach", communicated to Pattern Recognition (Elsevier), Avisek Gupta, Shounak Datta, Swagatam Das.
- "Fast Automatic Estimation of the Number of Clusters from the Minimum Inter-Center Distance for Center-Based Clustering", *under revision for publication in Pattern Recognition Letters (Elsevier)*, Avisek Gupta; Shounak Datta; Swagatam Das.
- "Multi-Objective Support Vector Machines: Handling Class Imbalance with Pareto Optimality", communicated after revision to IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks and Learning Systems, Shounak Datta, Swagatam Das.

Professional activities

Reviewer Duties

2017-now Pattern Recognition (Elsevier)2016-now Information Sciences (Elsevier)

2015-now IEEE Transactions on Systems, Man, and Cybernetics: Systems

2015-now Neurocomputing (Elsevier)

2014-now Engineering Applications of Artificial Intelligence (Elsevier)

Ninth International Conference on Advances in Pattern Recognition Eight International Conference on Advances in Pattern Recognition

Talks & lectures

"Data Irregularities in Pattern Classification", SSCVGIP 2018, Electronics and Communication Sciences Unit,

Indian Statistical Institute, Kolkata.

²⁰¹⁴ "Evolutionary Algorithms", Lectures on Soft Computation, Electronics and Communication Sciences Unit,

Indian Statistical Institute, Kolkata.

Personal information & contact details

Born September 03, 1989, Kolkata, India.

Nationality Indian

Languages known English (well-versed, fluent) * Bengali (mother language) * Hindi (fluent)

Extracurricular interests Painting, Calligraphy, Micrography, Graphic narratives Residence AD-169/2, Samar De Sarani, Barowarital, Krishnapur, 700102.